A woman in trouble
Inland Empire is a horror, thriller, mystery film directed by David Lynch.
When actress Nikki Grace gets the lead role in a cursed film, her world becomes more and more surreal,
blending realities and ideas of infidelity, reincarnation, and supernatural forces.
Nikki Grace / Susan Blue, played by Laura Dern.
Kingsley Stewart, played by Jeremy Irons.
Devon Berk / Billy Side, played by Justin Theroux.
Freddie Howard, played by Harry Dean Stanton.
Lost Girl, played by Karolina Gruszka.
Piotrek Krol, played by Peter J. Lucas.
Inland Empire is a 2006  film written, directed, shot, edited, and scored
by David Lynch, who produced it alongside Mary Sweeney.
The film stars Laura Dern as a Hollywood actress who begins to take on the personality of a character she plays
in a supposedly cursed film production, causing fragmented and nightmarish events to unfold.
It has defied categorization, with its genre being variously interpreted as drama,
experimental, fantasy, mystery, neo-noir, psychological thriller, and surrealist.
A co-production between the United States, France, and Poland, Inland
Empire takes its name from a Californian metropolitan area.
It was completed over a three-year period, shooting
primarily in Los Angeles and Łódź.
The process marked several firsts for Lynch: the film was shot without a finished screenplay, instead being largely developed on a
scene-by-scene basis, and was filmed entirely by Lynch on low-resolution digital video with a handheld Sony DCR-VX1000 camcorder.
The cast includes frequent Lynch collaborators such as Dern, Justin Theroux, Harry Dean
Stanton, and Grace Zabriskie, as well as Jeremy Irons, Karolina Gruszka, Peter J.
Lucas, Krzysztof Majchrzak, and Julia Ormond.
Brief appearances are made by additional actors including Terry Crews,
Laura Harring, Nastassja Kinski, Diane Ladd, William H.
Macy, and Mary Steenburgen.
The voices of Harring, Naomi Watts, and Scott Coffey are also heard in scenes where
characters watch excerpts of Lynch's short online horror series Rabbits (2002).
The soundtrack features a variety of musicians such as Beck, Dave
Brubeck, Kroke, Krzysztof Penderecki, and Nina Simone.
Inland Empire premiered at the 63rd Venice International Film Festival, where
Lynch was awarded the Golden Lion for Lifetime Achievement.
In a publicity stunt intended to increase Dern's chances of nomination for the Academy Award for Best Actress, which was ultimately unsuccessful, Lynch
chatted to bystanders on Hollywood Boulevard while sitting in a director's chair placed between a live cow and a large poster of Dern.
The film grossed $4.4 million on a budget of around $3 million.
It was named the joint-second-best film of 2007 by Cahiers du cinéma, and was listed on Sight and Sound's
films of the decade, as well as The Guardian's 10 most underrated movies of the decade.
The film was remastered by Lynch and Janus Films in 2022.
Lynch died in 2025, making Inland Empire his final film.
The film explores themes of homeless person,
gypsy, wife, identity, movie business.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.